Guide to the Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan, Yale University, records
1970-1990
RU 79
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
The records consist of conference materials documenting the Yale Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan (MEChA), African American Studies, the Black Student Alliance at Yale, and a study documenting conferences on AIDS and HIV infections.
Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan (New Haven, Conn.)
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is partially restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
The Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan (MEChA) was founded in 1968 as Los Hermanos and changed its name to United Mexican American Students (UMAS) when Yale College started admitting women in 1969. Later in 1969, the group changed their name to its current form.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of conference materials documenting the Yale Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan (MEChA), African American Studies, the Black Student Alliance at Yale, and a study documenting conferences on AIDS and HIV infections.
College students -- Societies, etc.; Mexican American students -- Societies, etc.; Black Student Alliance at Yale; Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan (New Haven, Conn.); Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Students
- Records, circa 1970-1988; Accession 1990-A-033
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 3 and 4 are open for research. The remainder of the accession is restricted until January 1, 2023.
  - Report of the Committee to Review the Status of Minority Students, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Yale Daily News, Yale related articles, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan (M.E.Ch.A) correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hispanics in the press, 1971-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles on Hispanic Issues (National Magazine), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Chicano Health Organization (NCHO), 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - M.E.Ch.A logo, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hispanics in the press; Rodriguez, Richard, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sol del Este, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - M.E.Cha.A library; Cruz, Ana, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Career services, "Getting a Federal Job", Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Latino Resources, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - S.A.C. transfers including original transfer sheet, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Presses, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Organizations and institutions mailing list, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Educational Neglect of Mexican American Students in the Lucia Mar Unified School District, Pismo Beach, California, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Ballad of Gregorio Cortez (Olmos, Edward James), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - La Causa, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Assertiveness Training Bibliography, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bonilla, Ruben, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Speaker's Forum Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Connecticut Humanities Council, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Church songs, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Theater, 1967-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Incas: Peruvian Art, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - M.E.Ch.A literary magazine, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Publications on Hispanic issues, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - (The) Murals of el Barrio, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Mexican American Women's National Association (MANA), 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mujeres Latinas, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Mexican art, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter to Advisory, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) brochure, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) correspondence, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letters, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - American Studies, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) C.V.s (parts I and II), 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC), 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) Affiliate correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) correspondence, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Periodical Acquisition, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Letter of Acquisition, Undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Letter to Advisory board members, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Arco Iris, staff recruit letters, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Arco Iris job descriptions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Arco Iris, "Call for Papers," original, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Stationary fliers and originals, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) events and publicity, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Yale buyer's guide, to purchase YCRC materials in town, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) Incorporation papers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Periodicals, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Research dialogue checklist, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Yale Chicano Research Center (YCRC) publicity/events, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Unrevised by-laws, Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Chicano literature publications and catalogues (parts I, II, and III), 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Decolonization, U.N. publication, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Politics of Mexico and Central America, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Central American Issues/Articles, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Alumni directories (M.E.Ch.A), 1969-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - El Mechero, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Directory supplement, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Admissions statistics, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chicano alumni directory, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Admitted minority students, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Admitted minority students, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Admitted minority students, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - El Mechero, student directory, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pachanga accommodations, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Originals of outgoing letters, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Student papers (parts I and II), 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Minority Advisory Council, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Recruitment conference, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Recruitment, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Grantsmanship, application for grants under the endowment grant program, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Grantsmanship, "Hispanics and Grantmakers", Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Grantsmanship information, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - M.E.Ch.A meetings, etc..., 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - MEChA Activities, fall, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - MEChA Activities, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Course and faculty, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Connecticut Association of Hispanic Healthcare, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - MEChA activities, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Speakers correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Pachanga, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - MEChA budget, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Chicano affairs activities, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Activities, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - MEChA general correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Tertulias, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Chicano affairs and correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - MEChA events, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Poster file, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - MEChA constitution, Undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Speakers forum checklist, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - MEChA library, Undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Senate congressional records, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Conversations with Winspread, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - MEChA newsletter, El Heraldo, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Conference on Movimiento Chicano at Yale University, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - El Heraldo, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - El Heraldo, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - MEChA newsletters: El Heraldo originals, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - El Heraldo Newsletter, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Heraldo, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - M.E.Ch.A. newsletters, 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Annual reports and notebooks and MEChA house, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chicano affairs annual reports, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Annual report, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - MEChA budgets, 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Treasurer's information, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Inter-Ivy travel, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hispanic Access to Higher Education, a Case Study of the Ivy League (parts I and II), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Report of the Governors Commission on Higher Education and the Economy, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - MALDEF, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Functional Prerequisition of a society, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Problem of the Marginal Man; Stonquist, E.V., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Age and sex categories, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - 100 percent American, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Science of Culture; Mintz, Sidney, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Mass Society and Extremist Politics, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Continuities and Discontinuities in Cultural Conditioning; Benedict, Ruth, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Immigrant Social Aspirations and American Education, 1880-1930 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Reform by FIAT, the Clark Plan in Washington, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Court Decisions and Educational Change, A Case History of the D.C. Public Schools, Undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Politics of Public Education in Block Chicago, 1910-1941 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Historical Analogies and Public Policy, The Black and Immigrant Experience in Urban America, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Philadelphia's South Italians in 1920s, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - The Races of Mankind, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Persistence of School Segregations in the Urban North: A Historical Perspective, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - School Enrollment: Chicago, 1925-1965 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - "Chicano Colleges," report prepared by Lopez, Hank, winter, and also material on other Chicano Colleges, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Intercultural Education, 1930-1941 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Community services, "Directory of Agencies Serving Hispanics in Connecticut", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Career and Education Services, organization listings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Abalos, Sociology-Religious studies, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Characteristics of Hispanic students in the New Haven public school system, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Research centers/country, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Chicanos and Higher Education, Undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - LULAC National Educational Service Centers, Inc. (LNESC), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Bilingualism, Bilingual education, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Mexican Literature, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - University of California, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Bibliography to Hispanic Literature at South Central Community College, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - MEChA budgets, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Financial records, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Fall '80 Conference, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Financial records, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Financial records, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Financial records, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Financial records, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Financial records, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Financial records, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Financial records, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Financial records, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - MEChA budgets, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Financial records, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - El Heraldo, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Speakers, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Print, media, and electronic coverage, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Chicano studies publications, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Senior essays (parts I, II, and III), 1971-1982 (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
  - Notebook, no title (parts I and II), 1982 (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
  - Latino Youth Development, Inc., 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
  - AZTLON East correspondence, members, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 26-28)
  - Affirmative action, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Pre Medical, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Job opportunities, Undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Campus minority groups, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Third World, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chicana, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Social Science and Sociology, 1949-1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minority pamphlets, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Revista Fall, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Agringado Joking Culture, 1975-1981 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chiconize, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - El Mechero, El Heraldo, Directories, etc..., 1976-1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - MEChA meeting agendas, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - MEChA history, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Arizona City, Tucson, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Farm workers information, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Minority statements and statistics, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Chicano resources, etc..., 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - MEChA materials, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Mail to Dean Ricardo and Avilia, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - MEChA directories, 1973-1984 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - General information, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Financial records, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Yale Daily News, Issue on Zionism, November 17, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Recruiting the Chicano Student: A Student Recruiter's Handbook, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Chicano students, 1971-1978 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Chicano: directory, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Cambios 5 Phideo, Undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - House history, MEChA, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - MEChA house fall, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - History MEChA and cultural centers, 1971-1983 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - History, minority cultural centers, 1979-1984 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - ChicanizARTE MEChA October Conference: Fall, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - MEChA, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - MEChA house, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Chicano center, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Correspondences, 1973-1983 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Pamphlets and newsletters, Undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Event posters, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Records, 1978-1990; Accession 1991-A-044
  Open for research.
  - Afro-American Studies 472b: Study of the History of the Black Student Alliance at Yale, 1978 May (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Unreconciled Nostalgia, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 4)
  - AIDS Conference: Participant Information (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AIDS Conference: Prevention and Beyond: A Framework for Collective Action, 1989 August (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
  - National Conference on the Prevention of HIV Infection and AIDS Among Racial and Ethnic Minorities, 1988 August (Box 2, Folder 8 - 9)
  - General Information, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10 - 11)